A Guide to the Colonial Williamsburg acquisition photographs, ca. 1930-1935
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Colonial Williamsburg acquisition photographs ca. 1930-1935
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 1994.4
140 items, 2 vols.
Approximately 140 photoprints documenting acquisitions for Colonial Williamsburg. Two photo albums documenting the restoration.
Perry, Shaw, & Hepburn
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1993
Biographical/Historical Information
Perry, Dean, Rogers & Partners, Architects, (then Perry, Shaw and Hepburn) was the firm selected by Rev. W.A.R. Goodwin and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. for the reconstruction of Colonial Williamsburg.
Scope and Content
Consisting entirely of photographs, this collection documents some of the many items acquired by Colonial Williamsburg as the restoration progressed in the 1930s. These items, including engravings, furniture, Delftware, pewter, and other household goods, comprise the first series.
The collection contains two series, photographs and albums. Within the photographs series are 6 subseries, each pertaining to the source of the acquisitions. Within each subseries items are listed alphabetically. An exception occurs in the Fridenberg and Miscellaneous subseries, where multiple portraits and engravings were photographed together. In both cases the subseries has been further divided to include a Multiple Images section.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Perry, Shaw, & Hepburn; Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Subjects:
Antiques.; Architecture - Virginia - Williamsburg; Historic buildings - Virginia - Williamsburg
Geographical Names:
Williamsburg (Va.) - Buildings, structures, etc. - Conservation and restoration.
Genre and Form Terms:
Black and white photographs.
Contents List
- Acquisitions
  - Dunwoody, Engravings, 1930s (10 items) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Addison, Joseph, Esq. (#324)
    - Boyle, Hon. Robert (#322)
    - Chaucer, Geoffrey (#327)
    - Locke, John, Esq. (#321)
    - Mary, Queen of England (#320)
    - Newton, Sir Isaac (#325)
    - Pope, Alexander Esq. (#326)
    - Washington, General George (#613)
    - William and Mary (#612)
    - William III, King of England (#323)
  - Flayderman collection, Furniture, 1934-1935 (11 items) (Folder 2)
    - "1 part cherry wood 3 part dining table" (#355, 2 copies)
    - "1 part cherry wood 3 part dining table" (#356, 2 copies)
    - "1 part cherry wood 3 part dining table" (#362)
    - Andirons, brass, pair (#360)
    - Andirons, two pairs (#363)
    - Arm chair, mahogany (#358)
    - Pine chest, carved and painted (#357)
    - Tea table, maple (#361)
    - Tools, fireplace (#610)
  - French, William A. and Co., Furniture, 1934-1935(23 items, many reference letter from William G. Perry to John D. Rockefeller, Jr.) OVERSIZE (Folder 3)
    - Bureau-Secretary (#24189)
    - Cabinet, 32.5" H x 6'1.75" W x 20" D (#39660/11)
    - Candlestick, 3' (#39660/31)
    - Candlestick, 3'2" (#39660/39)
    - Chaise lounge with cane or rush work, ornate carving, 44" H x 5' W, 21.5" D (#37777)
    - Chandelier (#39759)
    - Chest, metal beads, 22.5" H x 39" W x 21" D, ca. 1683 (#39660/15)
    - Double candlestick, 14" x 22" (#39660/4)
    - Fire back, Biblical scene, 27.5" x 39" (#39675)
    - Fire back, man and lion, 24" x 32" (#39677)
    - Fire back, woman at well, 22" x 30" (#39671)
    - Fireback with lion and unicorn, contains date 1618 32" H x 35" W (#23219)
    - Label in bureau bookcase
    - Mirror sconce (#21107)
    - Ornate fireplace set, no number
    - Painting, believed to be Dutch, 28" x 31.5", (#36306)
    - Plant stands, pair, possibly mahogany (#4646)
    - Rug, Oriental, 10'7" x 19'6" (#17700)
    - Rug, Oriental, 12'2" x 11' (#14916)
    - Rug, Oriental, 15' x 15' (#32872)
    - Secretary (2 photos, one with desk open, #37860)
    - Side chair (#37082)
  - Fridenberg, Engravings, 1934-1935 (21 items) (Folder 4)
    - "An Emblem of America", Published April 21, 1800 by P. Stampa (#493)
    - "Europe", Published August 14, 1801 by P. Concena (#495)
    - "Hunting Plate I: Brushing into Cover" and "Hunting Plate III: At Fault" (#573)
    - "Hunting Plate II: The Chase" and "Hunting Plate IV: The Death" (#572)
    - "The Extraordinary and Facetious History of John Gilpin…" (#43)
    - "View of the Attack on Bunker's Hill with the Burning of Charles Town, June 17, 1775", Engraved for Barnard's New Complete Authentic History of England, Drawn by Mr. Millar, Engraved by Lodge (#33)
    - Firebacks (3), different sizes, no identification
    - Map, "York Town in Virginia and Adjacent Country", drawn by J.F. Renault (#597)
    - Map, Terrae Marie Nova et Virginiae (#44)
    - Multiple images
      - Blenheim House, A view of the House of Commons, A view of the House of Peers
      - D. Clavdivs Caesar, D. Vespasianvs Avgvstvs, C. Caesar Caligvla, and C. Ivlivs Caesar. (#28)
      - Dramatic Action Illustrated…, A Man of Importance, Awkward Squads studying the Graces (#37)
      - Edmond Waller, Esq., unidentifiable image, and The Adelphi Terrace (#600)
      - Gaming House, Messers Harding, Howell, & Co., New Drury Lane Theatre, untitled (#40)
      - Godfridus Kneller Eques...; Louis XVI, King of France; His Excellency, John Duke of Marlborough… (#599)
      - King George I and William, Duke of Gloucester. Both at Kensington Palace. (#49)
      - Richard Boyle, Earl of Burlington, Mrs. Garrick, George the Third, King of Great Britain, France & Ireland, etc. (#598)
      - Sir Edward Coke, Lord Chief Justice and Anne of Denmark, Queen of K. Iames I. (#51)
      - Sir Samuel Garth, M.D. and Thomas Lord Fairfax (#48)
      - "The Engagement of Captn. Pearson in His Majesty's Ship Serapis…" (Drawn by Hamilton, Engraved by R. Collier), "The French Admiral Count DeGrasse Delivering his Sword for Admiral (now Lord) Rodney…" (Hamilton delin., Thornton Sculp.), and "The Unfortunate Death of Major Andre" (Hamilton delin., Goldar sculp.). All Engraved for Barnard's New Complete Authentic History of England (#32)
      - The Royal Academy, Inner Temple Court, Temple Bar, A Perspective View of Westminster Hall with both Houses of Parliament assembled on the Tryal of Simon Lord Lovat (#602)
  - Middlekoop, Delftware, Pewter, etc., 1934-1935 (18 items) (Folder 5)
    - Candlesticks (2), pewter (#377)
    - Ink stand, pewter (#378)
    - Inkwell, Louis XIV marble pewter (#117)
    - Measures(6, assorted sizes), pewter, 18th century (#119)
    - Mugs (5), Pewter, English, 18th century (#118)
    - Pewter, salt, pepper, and mustard (#121)
    - Plaque, Delft, 1627 (#115)
    - Plaques (2), polychrome,17th century, (#116)
    - Plaques (4 large), pewter, ca. 1740-1760 (#532)
    - Plate, Delft, claw mark (#82)
    - Plate, Delft, claw mark (#83)
    - Plate, small, basket pattern, mid 18th century (#535)
    - Plates (2 small), blue white, 18th century (#534)
    - Plates (2 small), Pompadour, 1735-45 (#539)
    - Plates (4 small), blue white, mid 18th century (#536)
    - Powder horn, shell shape (#538)
    - Snuff jar, Delft (#537)
    - Vase, pewter (#379)
  - Miscellaneous Sources, Purchases and gifts, 1930-1931 (57 items) (Folder 6)
    - Andiron, large, single iron, (#49)
    - Andirons (#255)
    - Andirons, attributed to Wren Building (#549)
    - Andirons, hand wrought (#336)
    - Arm chair (#145, 3 copies, various sizes)
    - Autographed prints of George Washington and William Wirt (#611, deaccessioned April, 1974)
    - Bookends (pair), lions (#408)
    - Bookends (pair), women reading (#419)
    - Boot rack (#11)
    - Bottle (#500)
    - Candlestick, brass, round saucer (#75)
    - Candlesticks (2), brass (#253)
    - Candlesticks (2), pewter (#254)
    - Candlesticks (2), pewter (#76)
    - Candlesticks (2), Wedgewood (#525)
    - Chair frame (#231)
    - Chestnut bottles (4) (#582)
    - Chestnut bottles (5), one with cork (#583)
    - Coffee grinder, box for twine, nutmeg grinder (#568)
    - Containers (3), one labeled "PLUM JAM", no number
    - Crate, wooden (#21)
    - Crate, wooden, lid open (#24)
    - Cupboard, no number
    - Desk, Chippendale(#219)
    - Dining chair (#241, 3 copies, various sizes)
    - Dining chair with arms, no number
    - Dresses (2), Queen Anne Spitalfields, silk (#87360)
    - Fireplace (#12446)
    - Forks and knives (12 pairs) (#498)
    - Frame (#615)
    - Garniture (5 pieces), mantle (#484)
    - Kettle with bob (#570) (Folder 7)
    - Knife box (#226)
    - Mirror (#223)
    - Multiple images
      - Framed photograph of Washington's headquarters at Newburgh, New York, and framed portraits of George and Martha Washington (#477)
      - Leather mug, round tea box, penny box, spice grinder, pepper container, no description (#496)
    - Needlework pieces, framed (#405)
    - Piano (#222)
    - Plate, shell shaped (#414)
    - Plates (6 small, 2 large), possibly pewter (#499)
    - Portrait, Randolph (#476)
    - Portrait, Waldo-Lafayette (#467)
    - Rug, Oriental (#593)
    - "Sheraton Sofa", very similar to Photograph #22, no number
    - Sofa, covered with plum colored horsehair, wooden pegs, no number
    - Sofa, displaying various stages of upholstery (#22)
    - Sundial (#585)
    - Table, Chippendale, three part (#225)
    - Trammel bars (2), wrought iron (#304)
    - Trivet (#497)
    - Tumblers with heavy bases (pair) (#584)
    - Weaving materials (#487)
    - Wine barrels (4) (#529)
- Albums
  - "An Album of Photographs of the Williamsburg Restoration", Williamsburg Holding Corporation, 1932.
  - Historic district, black and white, 4x6", 23 pp., ca. 1940